Morris K. Udall oral history collection, 1996-ongoing
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Morris K. Udall oral history collection, 1996-ongoing
MS 396
University of Arizona
The Morris K. Udall Oral History Project includes interviews with former Presidents, former and current Congressmen and Senators, journalists and intellectuals, key staff members and campaign aides, family members and friends. Topics covered include early Arizona history, Congressional history, Alaska wilderness preservation, the Central Arizona Project, bipartisanship in a less polarized time, life on the presidential campaign trail, the beginning of the end of the Vietnam War, the beginnings of the Democratic Study Group, and the role of poker-playing in congressional politics.
4 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Biographical Note
Morris "Mo" King Udall of Tucson, Arizona was born in St. Johns, Arizona on June 15, 1922. He entered the United States Army-Air Force as a private in 1942 and was discharged as a captain in 1946, having served in the Pacific Theatre. He was awarded a J.D. degree from the University of Arizona in 1949. Morris K. Udall was elected to his seat in the 87th Congress in 1961. He served in each succeeding Congress until his resignation on May 4, 1991. Morris K. Udall served as chairman of the U.S. House of Representatives Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs from 1977 to 1991. He also was the ranking member of the Committee on Foreign Affairs. He was a candidate in the Democratic primaries for President in the 1976 national campaign.
Organization
The collection is divided into three series. All series are organized alphabetically by individual.
Series 1: Audiocassettes, 1996-2006
Series 2: Compact Discs, 1996-2006
Series 3: Transcripts, 1996-2006
Scope and Content Note
The Morris K. Udall Oral History Project is generously funded by the Morris K. Udall Foundation and administered by the University of Arizona Library Special Collections. Its goal is to collect, preserve, and make available an archive of spoken recollections that illuminate the lives and careers of Congressman Udall and the Udall family. The interviews are not intended to be memorials to Congressman Udall or to the Udall family, but rather to advance an understanding of the major issues, events, and personalities of their times.
Those interviewed include former Presidents, former and current Congressmen and Senators, journalists and intellectuals, key staff members and campaign aides, family members and friends. Topics covered include early Arizona history, Congressional history, Alaska wilderness preservation, the Central Arizona Project, bipartisanship in a less polarized time, life on the presidential campaign trail, the beginning of the end of the Vietnam War, the beginnings of the Democratic Study Group, and the role of poker-playing in congressional politics.
Although several themes emerge from these interviews, a few stand out for their consistency. Among them was Mo Udall's leadership style, a style that emphasized respect for one's opponent and an understanding that "one can disagree without being disagreeable." Another was his use of self-deprecating humor to break the ice, defuse tension or frustration, to encourage consensus, or simply to make someone feel more comfortable.
New interviews are added periodically.
Udall, Morris K.; Udall, Morris K. -- Interviews.; Udall, Morris K. -- Anecdotes.; Arizona -- History.; United States. Congress -- History.; Conservation of natural resources -- Alaska.; Central Arizona Project (U.S.); United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century.; Ex-presidents -- United States -- Interviews.; Anderson, John -- interviews.; Ares, Charles E. -- Interviews.; Bracy, Terrence -- Interviews.; Broder, David -- Interviews.; Carter, Jimmy 1924- -- Interviews.; Chandler, Thomas -- Interviews.; Cox, Archibald 1912- -- Interviews.; Darden, George "Buddy" -- Interviews.; Dudley, Dudley -- Interviews.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913- -- Interviews.; Gabusi, John B. -- Interviews.; Galbraith, John Kenneth, 1908- -- Interviews.; Harris, Fred R. 1930- -- Interviews.; Lujan, Manuel 1928- -- Interviews.; McCain, John 1936- -- Interviews.; McNulty, James F. 1925- -- Interviews.; Obey, David -- Interviews.; Reuss, Henry S. -- Interviews.; Rhodes, John J. (John Jacob), 1916- -- Interviews.; Robertson, Cliff -- Interviews.; Seiberling, John -- Interviews.; Simpson, Alan K. -- Interviews.; Steiger, Sam -- Interviews.; Trautwein, Mark -- Interviews.; Udall, David B. "Burr" -- Interviews.; Udall, Elma -- Interviews.; Udall, Norma Gilbert -- Interviews.; Udall, Stewart L. -- Interviews.; Udall, Tom. -- Interviews.
Container List
- Series 1: Audiocassettes, 1996-2006
  - Anderson, John. (2) 1998 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ares, Charles. 1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bracy, Terry. (2) 2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Broder, David. 1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Carter, Jimmy. 2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chandler, Thomas. (2) 1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cox, Archibald. 1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Darden, George "Buddy". 2000 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dudley, Dudley. 1999 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ford, Gerald. 1999 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Gabusi, John. (2) 2005 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Galbrath, John K. 1999 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Harris, Fred. 2000 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Harris, Fred. 2000 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - King, Larry L. (2) 2006 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Lujan, Manuel. 2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Mathews, Jessica T. 2006 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - McCain, John. 2002 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - McNulty, James. (2) 1998 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mikva, Abner. 2005 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Neuman, Robert. 1999 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Obey, David. 1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Olson, Richard. (3) 1998 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Reuss, Henry. 2002 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Rhodes, John. (2) 1997 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Robertson, Cliff. (2) 1999 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Seilberling, John. (2) 1998 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Simpson, Alan K. 1999 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Steiger, Sam. 2001 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Trautwein, Mark. (2) 1998 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Travel and Advance Staff. (2) 1999 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Udall, D. Burr. (3) 1998 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Udall, Elma. 1996 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Udall, Elma. (2) 2004 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Udall, Elma. (3) 2004 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Udall, Elma; Whitting, Eloise Udall; Whitting, Warren. (2) 1996 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Udall, Norma. (2) 2003 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Udall, Stewart. (3) 1996 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Udall, Tom. (2) 1996 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Van Deerlin, Lionel. 2006 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Waldie, Jerome. 2006 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Wright, Jim. 2006 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Series 2: Compact Discs, 1996-2006
  - Anderson, John. (3) 1998 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Ares, Charles. (2) 1998 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Bracy, Terry. (3) 2000 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Broder, David. 1999 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Carter, Jimmy. 2000 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Chandler, Thomas. (3) 1998 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Cox, Archibald. 1999 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Darden, George "Buddy". 2000 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Dudley, Dudley. 1999 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Ford, Gerald. 1999 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Gabusi, John. (4) 2005 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Galbrath, John K. 1999 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Harris, Fred. (3) 2000 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Lujan, Manuel. 2000 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - McCain, John. 2002 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - McNulty, James. (3) 1998 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Mikva, Abner. (2) 2005 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Neuman, Robert. (2) 1999 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Obey, David. 1999 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Olson, Richard. (5) 1998 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Reuss, Henry. (2) 2002 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Rhodes, John. (4) 1997 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Robertson, Cliff. (3) 1999 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Seilberling, John. (3) 1998 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Simpson, Alan K. 1999 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Steiger, Sam. 2001 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Trautwein, Mark. (5) 1998 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Travel and Advance Staff. (3) 1999 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Udall, David B. (5) 1998 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Udall, Elma. (2) 1996 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Udall, Elma. (9) 2004 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Udall, Elma; Whitting, Eloise Udall; Whitting, Warren. (2) 1996 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Udall, Norma. (3) 2003 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Udall, Stewart. (5) 1996 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Udall, Tom. (3) 1996 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Van Deerlin, Lionel. (2) 2006 (Box 5, Folder 363)
  - Wright, Jim. (2) 2006 (Box 5, Folder 37)
- Series 3: Transcripts, 1996-2006
  - Anderson, John. 1998 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Ares, Charles. 1998 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Bracy, Terry. 2000 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Broder, David. 1999 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Carter, Jimmy. 2000 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Chandler, Thomas. 1998 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Cox, Archibald. 1999 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Darden, George "Buddy". 2000 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Dudley, Dudley. 1999 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Ford, Gerald. 1999 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Gabusi, John. 2005 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Galbrath, John K. 1999 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Harris, Fred. 2000 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - King, Larry L. 2006 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Lujan, Manuel. 2000 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Mathews, Jessica T. 2006 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - McCain, John. 2002 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - McNulty, James. 1998 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Mikva, Abner. 2005 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Neuman, Robert. 1999 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Obey, David. 1999 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Olson, Richard. 1998 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Reuss, Henry. 2002 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Rhodes, John. 1997 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Robertson, Cliff. 1999 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Seilberling, John. 1998 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Simpson, Alan K. 1999 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Steiger, Sam. 2001 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Trautwein, Mark. 1998 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Travel and Advance Staff. 1999 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Udall, David B. 1998 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Udall, Elma. 1996 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Udall, Elma. 2004 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Udall, Elma; Whitting, Eloise Udall; Whitting, Warren. 1996 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Udall, Norma. 2003 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Udall, Stewart. 1996 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Udall, Tom. 1996 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Van Deerlin, Lionel. 2006 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Waldie, Jerome. 2006 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Wright, Jim. 2006 (Box 8, Folder 10)